Sorensen, Jonathan; Papers apap350
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Jonathan Sorensen Papers1973-2004
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Sorensen, Jonathan R. (Jonathan Roger), 1965-
apap350
0.38 cubic ft.
This collection consists of Professor Jonathan Sorensen's audio and paper materials documenting the 1973 re-establishment of the death penalty in Texas.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Jonathan Sorenesen donated his papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2007.
Biographical History
Jonathan Sorensen, Ph.D. is a Professor in the Department of Criminal Justice, College of Human Ecology, at East Carolina University and previously served as a professor in the Department of Justice Studies at Prairie View A&M University. He is the author of numerous books and articles on capital punishment, criminal justice education, and corrections, several focusing on the death penalty in Texas. This includes Lethal Injection: Capital Punishment in Texas during the Modern Era (2006), The Rope, The Chair, and the Needle: Capital Punishment in Texas, 1923-1990 (1998), co-authored with James W. Marquart, Sheldon Ekland-Olson, and "Life and death in the lone star state: Three decades of violence predictions by capital juries," which appeared in Behavioral Science & the Law (January/February 2011).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to Jonathan Sorensen's interest in Texas capital punishment history. It features audio cassette tapes of hearings from the Texas House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence for HB 200, 63rd Legislature, which re-enacted the death penalty in Texas in 1973. The collection also consists of paper legislative materials related to the 1973 bill, clippings, notes and background research.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Capital Punishment--Texas; Legislative Hearings--Texas; Bills (legislative records); Correspondence; Testimonies; Legislative Records; Sorensen, Jonathan R. (Jonathan Roger), 1965-
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, February 6, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 1)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, HB 200, 63rd Legislature, Tape 1, February 6, 1973 (Cassette 1)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, HB 200, 63rd Legislature, Tape 2, February 6, 1973 (Cassette 2)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, HB 200, 63rd Legislature, Tape 3, February 6, 1973 (Cassette 3)
- Texas House of Representatives, Floor Proceedings, May 8, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 2)
- House Journal, May 8, 1973; May 10, 1973; May 28, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 3)
- Testimony on House Bill 200, May 23, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 4)
- Conference Committee Report, May 28, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 5)
- House Bill 200 and Amendments, May 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 6)
- News Clippings about Death Penalty Legislation, May 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 7)
- Excerpt from Eyewitness about Last Execution (1964) Using Electric Chair in Texas, 1973 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 8)
- "Comments, House Bill 200: The Legislative Attempt to Reinstate Capital Punishment in Texas," Houston Law Review, 1974 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 9)
- Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, March 1, 1977 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 10)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, 65th Legislature, Tape 1, March 1, 1977 (Cassette 4)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, 65th Legislature, Tape 2, March 1, 1977 (Cassette 5)
- House Committee on Criminal Jurisprudence, 65th Legislature, Tape 3, March 1, 1977 (Cassette 6)
- HB 945-65th, House Floor Tape Excerpts: 2nd and 3rd Readings, April 20-21, 1977 (Cassette 7)
- "Statute Note: Criminal Procedure - Capital Punishment - Texas Statutes Amended to provide for Execution by Intravenous Injection of a Lethal Substance," St. Mary's Law Journal, 1977 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 11)
- News Clippings about Death Penalty, 1977 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 12)
- "Corrections Law Developments: Execution by Lethal Injection," by Scott Christianson, 1979 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 13)
- News Clippings about Charlie Brooks, Jr. Execution, First Lethal Injection, 1982 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 14)
- Gov. Perry's Veto of House Bill No. 236, June 17, 2001 (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 15)
- Reference and Research, 2004; Undated (Box 1 (Jonathan Sorensen Papers), Folder 16)